[Music]
more than 50 of men in their 50s and 70
or more of men in their 60s suffer from
benign prostatic hypertrophy or bph
otherwise known as an enlarged prostate
this can result in burdensome lower
urinary tract symptoms such as having to
get up frequently at night to pee
current medical treatments are
clinically effective but their efficacy
is compromised by side effects and low
compliance rates symptoms include sexual
dysfunction high-grade prostate cancer
and depression
no wonder there's poor compliance and
when medication treatment fails surgical
procedures are considered such as
transurethral resection of the prostate
there has got to be
a better way
population studies suggest that low
intake of animal protein and high intake
of fruits and vegetables may be
protective but not just cutting down on
any animal protein eggs and poultry
seemed to be the worst along with
refined grains but no association was
found for red meat or dairy
population studies aside are there any
foods that have been put to the test
there have been more than 30 randomized
control trials on the herb saw palmetto
and it's been found to be
totally useless
evidently cranberries were used by
native americans to treat urinary
ailments but you don't know until you
put them to the test
now when they say dried cranberries
they're not talking about those sugary
oily craisins but rather just straight
whole cranberry powder and
significant improvements we're seeing in
bph symptoms quality of life and all
urination parameters for just about a
teaspoon a day of powdered cranberries
so we know a teaspoon works but what
about a third of a teaspoon or a sixth
of a teaspoon they also helped the
results from that one teaspoon of
powdered cranberries from the last study
would equate to this
and now this study used a supplement
because it was funded by the supplement
company but the supplement is just
straight cranberry powder so you might
as well just buy it in bulk for much
cheaper and just add it to a smoothie or
something
what about using a berry that's a little
tastier like drinking purple grape juice
no
benefit whatsoever
in a previous video i talked about the
use of flax seeds
which may have a therapeutic efficacy
comparable to that of commonly used
drugs with only good side effects ok
so what about other seeds pumpkin seeds
have evidently been used in folk
medicine as a remedy for prostate
disorders for centuries and in a petri
dish they can cut the growth of bph
prostate cells in half
scientists have also injected pumpkin
seed extracts into rabbits but
what about people
pumping seed oil appears to help with
prostate issues when pitted head to head
against the drug prosocian it seemed to
work as well as the pill same when it
was head to head against the drug
terazosin
what they didn't have though is a
placebo group it would have been nice to
see how well the pumpkin seed oil
supplements did against placebo and
hey in an ideal world i'd love to also
see a group just given whole pumpkin
seeds themselves and
boom there it is
more than a thousand men were randomized
either a pumpkin seed extract a placebo
or just about a tablespoon a day of
plain pumpkin seeds
the study was funded by the drug company
that made the supplement but the
supplement flopped it was no better than
placebo but the pumpkin seeds themselves
worked the supplement appeared to reduce
symptoms but not better than placebo
however just the plain old seeds did
so wasn't just some compound extracted
from the oil and in fact we've since
learned that even an oil-free extract
seemed to work bottom line the
researchers concluded is that pumpkin
seed could be recommended for bph
patients with mild to moderate symptoms
this conclusion was echoed by the
european equivalent of the fda pumpkin
seeds can be used for the relief of
lower urinary tract symptoms related to
an enlarged prostate after more serious
conditions have been excluded by a
medical doctor
[Music]
so
you